At the start of the course I showed a diagram of the worldwide web,
which we can think of it as a directed graph where the nodes
are the documents that are available on the web.
How can we take advantage of the structure of the web of all those documents
as we're putting together our own web applications, and
how can we do that using a framework such as React?
So, how was web development done in the old days, let's say,
the early to mid 1990s?
Here, we see a piece of C code that's handling everything that would have to
happen, including handling an incoming HTTP request,
generating the HTML content and sending back an HTTP response.
We can think of this as a monolithic approach to web development.
All of the code, all of the functionality is in one place.
So, how can we improve on this?
Well, we can best practices from software engineering.
One of those is modularity, where we break up the code in distinct components.
Each component services a specific purpose or goal.
We can also use a notion of functional independence.
Each component is able to do its job with minimal dependence on other components,
and the interaction between these components is done in
a standardized manner.
This allows us to change the different components without having to
change other components.
That's known as stability, and there's less dependency and
less coupling between each component.
This gave rise to an approach to developing web applications,
known as a service oriented architecture.
This approach was first identified in a letter to Amazon employees around 2002.
Where it was pointed out that the Amazon employees and the developers of the Amazon
software needed to expose their data and functionality through service interfaces.
That is that the only communication between the different parts of code
would be through these interfaces which had to be standardized.
They needed to be designed from the ground up to be externalizable, so
they could be used by other groups.
And each team needed to plan this in advance, knowing that perhaps
developers outside the organization will need to use them, as well.
Nowadays, we talk about Software as a Service or SaaS.
This extends the idea of service oriented architecture.
And now the entire software runs as a service that is the client or end
user is simply a composition of different services that are available on the web.
Here I list out many of the advantages of Software as a Service.
The point is that the user might have a web browser, but
that's the only software that they need to install.
This makes it easy to add new features, add new data sets, and
the user doesn't have to worry about, for instance, losing data or
being behind with different versions of the software.
On this slide I introduce this notion of microservices.
These images came from Martin Fowler,
where he's pointing out that in the old days of the monolithic web application,
all of the functionality was in a single process as we can see up here.
The different colored shapes indicate different pieces of functionality.
If we wanted to scale that, so that many different users on the web
could use that different functionality, we would have to do that by replicating
the entire application or process onto multiple servers.
With Software as a Service, or SaaS, which is a microservice as architecture,
now each instance does one particular task, or provides one particular service.
And we can scale this by aggregating the different services, as needed,
as shown down here, but only replicating
the services that need to be replicated and not replicating the entire process.
So how do these services interact with each other and
how does the client or browser interact with these services?
These days we use a notation known as REST or REpresentational State Transfer.
In REST, we think about the content on the web as resources.
Not necessarily pages but data that we can access through a standard mechanism.
That standard mechanism is usually known as an API or
Application Programming Interface.
Now APIs exist in just about every programming language, but
in web programming we think of the API as some URL or
set of URLs that gives us data that we can then include in our web application.
In the rest of this lesson I'm going to show you an example of how we can use
a RESTful API to get content from the New York Times newspaper and
include it in our web application using a react component.
The New York Times is an American Daily newspaper, and they provide a variety
of APIs that allow developers to access article data about books, movies, etc.
In this example, going to create a web app that displays clickable New York Times
articles and images.
To get started, we need to let the New York Times know that we're going to be
accessing their API, by requesting a developer key shown at this URL.
Once you have that developer key, you can test out the API, and
seeing what the data looks like by going to this URL.
Let's see how we would do this in React.
First we'll create a React component named,
ArticlesGrid that we're going to drop into our page to display all of the data.
As we saw in previous lessons, ArticlesGrid will extend React.Component,
it will have a constructor that sets its properties, and
then we'll initialize the state to an empty array called articles.
Now we'll go out on the web and get the data from the New York Times.
We do this in the componentDidMount function.
This is the callback function that's called immediately after
the component is mounted in the virtual dom.
Then we have the URL that we'll use to access the New York Times API.
The first part of the URL is standard for anyone accessing the API.
The second part includes your specific API key which you would receive
when you register as a developer.
Now, we'll request the data using this call here,
which is part of the jQuery AJAX library.
Although we haven't looked into that, suffice it to say, that this function call
will allow us to make an HTTP request to the URL that we just specified.
And when the HTTP response comes back, it will invoke this function.
This function will then set the the state of this React.Component.
That is, we'll call setState so that the component will re-render.
And we'll set the articles variable
to the return value of this.parse, which we'll see in a subsequent slide.
This.parse will take the data that comes back in that HTTP request.
Then we'll bind the result back to this React.Component.
Here's just a tiny piece of the data that comes back from the New York Times API.
It uses JSON, which is the JavaScript Object Notation
which is just a string representation of an object.
This object has an attribute called response which is also an object.
One of the attributes or properties of that object is this meta information.
And then there's an array called docs.
In that array, we have an object for each document and
it has properties such as the URL, the snippets or
a small piece of text, the lead paragraph or first paragraph, and much, much more.
Following that would be the next article, which is another object and so on.
So we see that the New York Times API will return a lot of raw data but
we only need a small part of it.
In particular, we only want the URL of the image that we want to display,
the title of the article, and then we'll link the URL back to the article.
So that the user can click it and go to the New York Times website.
So let's see how we would parse that data that comes back from the API
into something that we can use in our React.Component.
Within our ArticlesGrid class we'll have a function called parse
that's going to take the results, or
the data that came back from making the API call to the New York Times.
First we'll do a little bit of error handling, and
see that if there are no results, that is if results is empty or null, and
there's no response in the results, then we'll just return an empty array.
Otherwise, in the results object, we'll get the response object,
that we saw in a previous slide.
And from that we'll get the docs,
which are all the documents that came back from that API request.
We'll declare an array called parsedArticles,
which will be the articles that we're going to return.
And now we'll start looping over all of the articles
that were in the response from the API.
We'll create a variable called article, which is just each individual article.
And then we'll apply this function here.
Article is the article we're considering.
Multimedia is a property in the article which contains the information
about the different media, for instance, the images.
Multimedia is an array so we're going to use the find function.
And we'll pass the find function,
the function called isXL that we've defined down here.
What this will do is let us find any multimedia where its
image.subtype is xlarge, because we only want to show extra large images.
If this article has multimedia which has an extra large image,
then we'll include it in our parsedArticles return value.
We'll use the push function on this array, and we'll create a new object as follows.
The object will have a property called id, which will come from the article.
And the object will have a title.
Now here we see a little bit of JavaScript trickery.
If this article has a main headline, then it will set the article to that.
However, if there is no main headline, then this would return undefined.
Undefined is a false value, so because we're using the or expression here,
it'll evaluate this part which will be Untitled, and set title to Untitled.
The object will also have the image URL where we'll apply this function
again to get the part of the multimedia that has the extra large image.
And we'll get its URL.
And as we saw on the previous line if this returns undefined then or
which is here will also evaluate this part and
will just set the image URL to the hash or pound sign.
Last we'll do the same for the web URL for this article.
So that when the user of our web app clicks it, they go to the New York Times.
Finally we'll return this array of parsed articles so
that they can be displayed in our React.Component.
Now we have the data, let's create a component that will display each article.
The code we see down at the bottom here is our React.Component, but
we're just using this shorthand notation, because it only has the render function.
So we'll create a variable, called article, and use this notation.
We're only defining the render function, and
part of the props for this React.Component is the article
that will be passed to it by the component that creates it.
We'll generate the URL for displaying the image and then for
this React.Component we're going to return the div.
Here we see that in this div we're going to put it into a CSS class.
You might say well,
wait a minute I thought to add it to a CSS class I would use the word class here.
However, because the word class is a reserved word in JavaScript,
we can't use it here.
So in React, if we want to add an HTML element to a CSS class,
we have to use className.
Here, we're putting this in the article class.
Within that div, we'll have our link.
This will also be in a class called article-link.
And the target of this link will be the web URL that came from the article
that was passed as the prop.
We'll have a clickable image that we'll also put into a CSS class.
We'll use the title, which will appear when the user hovers or
mouses over the image and then the source of the image.
Finally, we're ready to put it all together by displaying it
in our ArticlesGrid React.Component.
The ArticlesGrid component will have a render function that's going to
also use a little bit of JavaScript trickery.
If this.state.articles is undefined, then it's a falsy value, and
false and anything will return false, so in this case we won't display anything.
However, if articles does exist, that's a truthy value, so
then we will display what comes next which is this div.
Remember that the ArticlesGrid had the articles that
was set in the componentDidMount function.
That's an array and we're going to use the math function on the array.
Recall that the math function applies
this argument function to each element of the array.
For each element of the array, then, we'll return the JSX with the article,
passing each article as a prop, and also passing a unique key.
In summary, in this lesson, we saw the service oriented architecture and
Software as a Service, which allow us to create
web applications simply by combining different online components.
And we saw how we could use RESTful APIs in React.