Last time, we saw how React components can react to user events and
change their appearance and create dynamic HTML based on their state.
Part of the point of React is that the components can interact with each other
and that one component can affect another.
In this lesson we'll see two such examples.
The first example is this filtered list.
At the top I have an input box that allows me to type some text.
And at the bottom I have a pre-populated list of animals.
In my input box, when I type the letter A, the list shrinks and
it removes all the animals that don't contain that A.
Or you can think of it as only showing the ones that do contain an A.
When I type more letters, for
instance N and T, I only see the words that contain ant.
The point here is that there are actually two components.
One is clearly this list that is dynamically changing based on what's
typed up here.
But this list, down here, is just a general dynamic list
that's part of an overall bigger component which is this whole thing.
Let's start with the outer component or the application itself.
This is a component I've called FilteredList.
As we saw in previous examples,
it has constructor that passes the properties to the super class constructor.
And it's going to create a local variable called allItems,
which is an array that's initialized with the names of the animals.
Then we'll initialize the state to have two parts.
First will be the initialItems, which is just the set of all the items, or
the array of allItems.
And then the currentItems which will be the thing that changes.
These are the items to be displayed.
Now, we have our callback function, called filterList.
It's going to create a local variable called updatedList initially set to
the initialItems, to all of the items.
And then it's going to modify updatedList as follows.
It's going to use the filter function on the updated list.
Remember, when called on an array the filter function returns
all of the elements in that array, whereby this function returns true.
So it will apply this function to all elements in the array and
return the elements for which it's true.
So here's what this function does.
For each item in the array, it's going to use the search function.
Remember that search looks through a string and
sees if it contains another string.
Here, the string that we're seeing if it contains
is the value that's typed into the input.
Which came from here as the argument to this function.
That will be what the user has typed into the box.
Search will return -1 if this string,
what they've typed into the box, is not found in the item itself.
So that way it will remove it or filter it out.
But search will return a positive number, the index, if the element,
or if the string is found in that string.
At the end of calling that line of code, updatedList will contain all of
the elements in the initialItems that do contain whatever was typed into the box.
And finally, it will update the state by calling this.setState and
setting the currentItems to that updatedList.
Now, we'll see the render function for our FilteredList component.
The render function will return this div
containing the input box where the user can type.
And when the input changes
then the filterList function that we saw on the previous slide will be invoked.
Now, we see how the FilteredList component uses another components.
When we render the FilteredList component,
we also rendered this ListItems component which we're going to create below.
This is how React components can interact with each other
where one contains another.
The prompts that we send to ListItems will be whatever the current items are in
the FilteredList state.
Now we see our ListItems compoent.
Although, it's defined in the same HTML page we could use this ListItems component
in any application where we just want a dynamically generated list of items.
It will only have this render function which is going to return
an unordered list.
It'll take the items that were passed as the properties when we created it in
the FilteredList, and it will use the map function on that items array.
Remember, the map function just applies this function to every item in the array.
And what this function is going to do is for
each item return this JSX which is the list item
specifying a unique key based on the item and then the value of the item.
Last, when we want to drop this into our HTML page, we only need
to render the FilteredList component which contains the list item components.
In this example, I have a to-do list.
I can type in the input box and then add it to a growing unordered list.
For instance, I'll type Learn JavaScript, I'll click the Add button, and
it will be added to our unordered lists.
I'll type something else like find happiness, add that, and so on.
When I click on an element in the unordered lists, it will cross it out, for
instance, to mark that I've done that, I've accomplished it.
In this case we actually have three layers of components.
Each element of our to-do list is itself a component,
the list itself is another component, and
then the entire thing is a third parent component.
Let's look at the code here, starting with the outer, or
the top level component, which I've called TodoApp.
As we've seen before, it has a constructor that passes the properties to the super
class constructor, and its state is going to contain three things.
Initially, the array of items will be empty.
The text appearing in the text box will be empty.
And then there will be some unique id for each element in the unordered list and
we'll initialize the id to 0.
Now, we have a call back function handleChange and
when handleChange is invoked, it's going to modify the state
by setting the text to whatever is typed into the box.
I have another call back function, handleSubmit, which we'll see in a moment,
is used when we submit the form and click the add button.
Now, because we're using a form and
by default submitting a form will reload the page.
We don't want that to happen.
So we need to use this preventDefault function
to not reload the page when we submit the form.
Then we'll create a new item, which is an object that has some text which is
going to be the text that came from this object state, and some unique id.
Last, when we submit the form,
we're gonna set the state of this outer component by concatenating or
adding the newly created item to the array of current items,
clearing the text, and updating the id.
Now, we'll see the render function for our TodoApp component.
The render function is going to return this div with the HTML header TO-DO LIST.
And then inside the TodoApp,
we have a TodoList component that we'll see on the next slide.
When we create the TodoList component, we're going to pass
this .state.items as the items props to that component.
Now, also in the TodoApp we have a form.
The form has the onSubmit event, and we're going to bind the onSubmit
event to the handleSubmit function that's defined in this component.
There's also the input box or input field.
We're going to bind the handleChange function in this component to the input
fields onChange event and we'll set it's value to this components state.text.
Last, we have the Add button that is part of the form.
Now, lets see the TodoList component.
Remember, within the TodoApp, the outer component, we're going to
render the TodooList and will pass it the items in the app to the list.
TodoList is of course React to component, but we just have the render function,
which is going to return this unordered list.
It'll take the items that were passed as the props when we created the TodoList.
As we saw on the previous example,
we'll map this function to each element in the item's array.
For each one we'll now return a TodoItem that has a unique identifier and
the text to display.
Finally, we see the TodoItem, the TodoItem, which is part of the TodoList,
is a react component that has a constructor, and has its own state.
Here we have a Boolean value, amDone, to indicate whether we've finished or
accomplished this item on our TodoList.
And we'll have a callback function for this particular element,
the particular list item which will be called handleClick which will flip or
toggle the amDone Boolean that's part of the state.
Now, when I render a TodoItem, I'll determine whether there should be a line
through the text using the ternary operator if amDone is true then,
we'll say line-through, otherwise, none.
And then when I render this one list item, I'll give it a unique key which
came from the properties that were passed to it when it was created.
I'll bind the handleClick function to the onClick event.
And then, I'll set the textDecoration style attribute to
either be line through or none and finally display the text.
In this lesson we've seen how React components can interact with each other
where one component includes another.
It can be difficult to think in terms of components when designing the HTML pages.
But in the next lesson, we'll see some of the advantages of doing so.