We've been looking at React, which allows us to create modular JavaScript
components for use in our web applications.
So far, we've been writing these components in our HTML pages.
But as the components get bigger, and
as we get more of them, the amount of code will start to grow.
So how can we separate these components into different files and
then include them into our application?
Here I'll introduce a tool called Node.
Node is a free, open source platform and
framework built in JavaScript, that we'll see a lot more in week four.
Node includes a suite of tools that allows the user to create any sort of JavaScript,
and thus, React application.
And most importantly, includes a tool called the Node Package Manager, or
npm, which allows us to install programs and manage dependencies.
Here we're going to see how we can use Node to help us deploy
a larger React application.
One of the benefits to using Node to deploy the React application is that
instead of including all of the JavaScript code within the script tags in the HTML,
now we can separate the components into different files
to make the code more modular.
Which means that it's easier to manage, easier to change, easier to understand.
In our JavaScript files,
Node allows us to incorporate dependencies using two keywords.
The first one is require, which says that we need to use this library.
And the other one is import, which is just shorthand for
importing code from another file into this file.
To install Node on your computer, just go to their website,
where you can download and install Node, and any appropriate packages.
Now we'll also need to use npm, or
Node Package Manager, which always comes with a Node installation.
But be sure to update to the most recent version using
the command we see here, which is npm install npm -g.
So why do we need to use a tool like Node when we're creating our React application?
Well, one reason is that we want to manage and include the different dependencies.
In the previous examples, we've seen that we need to include the React library,
the React-DOM library, etc., and a tool like Node will help us manage all of that.
Some browsers only support older versions of JavaScript, and
as we'll see later in the course, we may want to use newer versions.
However, somehow we have to make sure that the code is compatible
with those old browsers.
We've been using JSX in our React component's render functions, but
we need to transform that into JavaScript.
And last, we want to have some modularity.
We want to be able to break up the different React modules or components
into separate files, and then bundle them together into a single application.
Node helps us address all of those things by incorporating a tool called Babel for
doing JSX and ES6 transformation.
ES6 is a newer version of JavaScript that we'll see later.
And incorporating a tool called Webpack which bundles all of the components into
a single application.
Once you've installed Node and npm, you can install this tool
using the command npm install -g create-react-app,
which will install the package that allows you to create React apps using Node.
Once you've installed it, you can run this command, create-react-app,
followed by the name of the directory where you want to install your app, and
this will set up a new React application on your computer.
Among the many files and directories that this will create on your computer,
there are three important ones.
The first one is package.json, this is the configuration file that
includes all the information about your app and the dependencies.
It'll also create a public directory.
This is where you'll put all of the static content, for instance, HTML images, etc.
And it will lastly create a source directory or src directory.
That's where it'll put executable things such as JavaScript.
So now you've downloaded and installed Node, you've used
the Node Package Manager, or npm, to install the create-react-app package.
And then you've used the create-react package to create a new application.
Now we're ready to start the default React application that you installed
by changing directory to that location, using Command Prompt or
Terminal, and then simply running the command npm start.
This will start a web server on your computer that's listening for
incoming HTTP requests on port 3000.
The port is simply part of the address.
It allows your computer to have multiple web servers running at the same time.
This one is listening on this particular port, which is number 3000.
Now if you'd like to see the default web application in your browser,
you can just open localhost:3000 from your computer.
And you'll see the default React application that looks like this.
We've seen how to install Node and
Node Package Manager, how to install the create-react-app package, and
then how to use the create-react package to create a React app.
Now, we've started the React app and we've gotten the default one.
But now let's see how we could modify it and add our own components.
In this simple example,
we'll add the Counter component that we created in a previous lesson.
This one just has the button that every time you click it,
it increments some counter, and
the number of times you've clicked the button is displayed in the page.
Rather than having the code for the Counter component in our HTML page,
we would put it in a separate file in the source directory called Counter.js.
At the top of that file, we would include this line that creates the variable called
React and uses the keyword require to say that we're requiring the react library.
Then we would create the Counter component just as we did before
by extending React.Component.
We'd still have the constructor, incrementCount function,
the render function.
All of that is exactly the same as before.
Now at the bottom of the file, we would say export default Counter,
which allows other JavaScript files to use the code,
in particular the Counter component that we've defined here.
Now that we've created our Counter component,
we want to use it in our React app.
src/App.js is the main component or the main piece of code for our app.
At the top of that file, we would use import Counter from and
then the name of the JavaScript file where we created Counter.
That just allows us to use the Counter component here in this file.
The App class is exactly the same as it was before.
But now we can use the Counter component by putting it in the render function,
and this will use our Counter.
On most computers the browser will in fact automatically refresh, and
we'll see now that our Count component has been included in our app.
We started this lesson talking about the problems of having many components within
the HTML page.
So now in this example,
we'll see where we have many components defined in many different files.
And then we'll talk about how can we test them?
How do we know that our application works correctly?
This example is known as the React Dogs example.
In this example, we have a list of dogs with their picture, their name,
and their breed.
And then in the bottom left we have a form
that allows us to add more dogs to the list.
When I put information into the form and
I click the Submit button, another dog will be added to the list.
And then when I click the little X next to the dog's breed,
that will remove the dog from the list.
So let's see, how did we do this in React, and how did we separate
the different components in different files and then combine them together?
In all of these React apps,
the parent of the entire app will be a component called App.
Inside the App component, we'll have a component called Dogs,
which will be the list of all the different dogs.
Inside the Dogs component, we'll have DogItems which has the dog picture, name,
and breed.
Also in the App component, we'll have an AddDog component,
which is the form that allows us to add a dog to the list.
This is the code for App.js.
A lot of it is similar to what we've seen before, but now, of course,
we're including code that we've written elsewhere.
At the top of App.js we need to import React, and
we'll also import Component, or React.Component, from the React library.
We're going to import the Dogs component that we've implemented in Dogs.js,
which I've put in the components folder, or directory.
Likewise, there will be an AddDog component that's in AddDog.js,
which is also in the components folder, or directory.
And lastly, for this app, we'll include a CSS file, called App.css.
Now we write our React component called App.
I won't show the details of the constructor, but
let's just say that the state of this app
includes the array of all the dogs that we're going to display.
We'll have a callback function, or a handler function, called handleAddDog,
which takes a dog object and will add it to the array.
Likewise, we'll have a handleDeleteDog function
that takes the name of the dog we want to remove from the array.
Now we have the render function,
which is going to return a div that's using the CSS class called App.
The render function is really the point of this example.
If we go back and look at the rendered webpage, we see that the App component,
which is the outer component, has two subcomponents, or
child components, Dogs, and AddDog.
In our JavaScript, we're going to include the Dogs component,
and we're going to pass it the array of dogs which is in the app state,
and we'll call the property dogs.
We'll also pass a property called onDelete, which is a reference
to the handleDeleteDog function that we've defined up here.
This will allow the Dogs component to invoke the handleDeleteDog function
defined in App.
Likewise, we'll include the AddDog component.
This is the form that allows us to add more dogs to the array.
And it will have a prompt called onAddDog,
which will be the handleAddDog function that we've defined up here.
We won't look at that example in any more detail,
because the point is simply that we can use the keyword import
to import the React components that we've defined in other .js files.
For the rest of this lesson, though, I wanna talk about testing.
How do we know that our React application is implemented correctly?
For testing our React app, we're going to use these three packages.
The first is Mocha, which is a test runner or
testing framework that can be used with any type of JavaScript code.
We'll also use Chai.
Chai is an assertion library that lets us easily check whether the behavior we're
seeing from our program is what we expected.
And last, we'll use Enzyme, which is a testing utility specifically for
React applications.
If we want to include Enzyme and Chai in our program,
we need to install those packages using this instruction here, npm install
--save-dev enzyme react-test-renderer chai.
Earlier, I mentioned that our JavaScript code would go in the source or src folder.
Within the source folder, we're going to create a subdirectory called tests,
where we'll put all of our test code.
By convention the name of the file that includes the test
would end with the .test.js extension.
For instance, if we're testing our Dogs component,
the convention would be to call that file Dogs.test.js.
When we used the create-react-app package to create our default React app,
it should have created the file App.test.js.
If not, you can certainly create this file on your own.
When we write our tests,
we need to make sure that we import the necessary components and libraries.
We, of course, need React and ReactDOM.
From Enzyme, we need these keywords mount and
shallow that we're going to use to create our React components.
And then from Chai, we'll use the keyword expect which
allows us to say what we expect to happen when we're testing our code.
So this would be App.test.js.
At the top, we're going to import React from the react library.
We're going to import the expect keyword, or function, from chai.
And we'll import mount and
shallow from enzyme, that we'll see in just a little bit.
We also need the component that we're actually testing, so
import App from the App.js file.
Now what we're doing is writing Mocha tests.
We'll use the Mocha testing framework to define and then execute our tests.
First, we'll use the keyword, or
function, describe, that allows us to describe a Test suite.
A Test suite is simply a collection
of test cases that are all trying to test the same piece of code.
In this case, the App component.
Here we have a comment or a message that describes what this Test suite does.
And then we have the function that includes all of our tests.
To write an individual test case, we use the keyword, or function, it.
The first argument to it is the string describing what we're testing here.
Here we're testing that there's only one element in the App CSS class.
Then we have the function, which is the test itself.
Here we'll create a constant called wrapper.
Here we're using the shallow keyword, or function,
that we've imported from Enzyme that allows us to create our React component.
shallow does a shallow creation which creates the component but
not the subcomponents, not its child components, for instance, Dogs or AddDog.
In this case, we're only creating an instance of the App component.
Now that we've created the component, we can specify what we expect to happen.
Using the expect keyword, or function,
that we've imported from Chai, we can say that when we use the wrapper and
try to find anything in the App CSS class that there should be something.
And in fact, there should only be one thing.
That is, there should only be one HTML element in the App CSS class
that would be in our App component.
Now let's see how we would test the relationships between different
components.
This code here could be in the same test file, in the same test suite, or
it could be in a different one.
As before, we're writing an individual test case,
which has the message of what we're testing,
that the Dog List contains two dogs, and then the function that runs this test.
We'll create our wrapper.
And now this time instead of using a shallow creation, we'll use the keyword,
or function, mount that we've imported from Enzyme.
mount will do a deep creation, that is, it will create not only the App component but
all of its dependencies and their dependencies and so on.
In this case, what we're expecting
is that we're able to find a Dogs component within the App component.
And within that, we should be able to find a DogItem component within Dogs.
And not only that there are any DogItems, but specifically that there are two
DogItems because, by default, we'll say there are two dogs in the array.
Now let's see how we can simulate the user interacting with our app
to make sure that the app behaves as we expected.
Again, this test case could be in a separate file or the same file.
Or in some other test suite.
Here we're testing that our app successfully adds a dog to the list
when we submit the form.
As we saw in the previous example, we'll mount the app component and
then we'll use that component to find the adddog component.
Remember adddog component was the form that allowed the user to enter information
about the new dog.
Now we want to simulate filing out the form and submitting the form.
So we'll use the AddDdog component and
we'll find an HTML element with the ID dogName.
This would be the input field from the form that was shown within this component.
Now we know that only one HTML element can have the id dogName,
but we still need to make sure that get the zero width element when it comes back.
Then we can specify the value of that HTML element and we'll set it to Lola.
Which simulates entering Lola into that HTML input field.
We'll do the same thing by putting a value into the imageURL field and
into the dogBreed field.
So now we've filled out the form.
Now we'll simulate submitting the form.
It's tempting to say that we should simulate clicking the button.
But with a React component, we actually just simulate the submission of the form.
In that adddog component, we'll find the HTML form element, and
then we'll call a simulate function on the form,
and we're simulating that we're submitting it.
Now that we've submitted the form, we expect that if
in our app component we should still be able to find a Dogs component.
Within the Dogs component we should still be able to find the DogItem component.
And now there should be three dog items, originally they were two and
now we just added another.
Not only should there be three dog items, but we also want to make sure that the dog
we added has the values that we entered in to the fields.
To do that we can access the app component state, using the state function.
And as I mentioned earlier,
we'll just say that in this state there's an array of dogs.
So we'll access element number two, which will be the third dog in the array,
and we'll check that the name is Lola
since that's the name that we entered into the form.
Last, let's see what happens when we try to delete one of the dogs
by clicking on the link that was next to the dog's breed.
Here we're writing the test case, we're mounting the app component.
Within the app components, we should be able to find a link using find,
and then a for the anchor.
We'll get the first link that we find, this will be the delete link.
And then we'll simulate clicking on that link.
Now we're expecting there to only be one dog.
You may say,
wait a minute, in the previous example we had three, why do we only have one?
Because each test starts with the original state.
In the original state we only had two dogs,
when we remove one now we're down to one.
So we've written all of our tests, now it's time to run them.
We can simply run the tests using the node package manager, in this command here,
npm run test.
If any of the tests fail, you'll see output that looks like this.
Here's the description of the test case that failed and here's what went wrong.
For instance, we expected some object to have a length of four, but
it got three, etc.
Down at the bottom here, you'll see all of the different test suites,
how many tests failed, how many tests passed, etc.
If all of the tests pass, then you'll see a message that looks like this.
To summarize, in this lesson we seen how we can use node to create React
applications that allow us to put our component code into separate .js files,
and then include them into our app as necessary.
We've also seen how we can use tools such as Mocha,Chai and
Enzyme to test our React applications.