When I started learning about React,
I thought how do I get one component to access or modify another?
I know how to do that for instance in jQuery, I can get and
HTML element by it's class or ID.
But in React, if I have one component, how can that then go get another component?
The solution is to use composition that we saw last time where one
component contains other components and that's how we'll get them to communicate
with each other as we'll see in this example.
Here I have an HTML page where I'm going to ask a user to enter two numbers and
then we'll multiply them immediately and show the product below.
Initially, the fields default to zero, so when the user types 8, nothing is shown.
But when they type 9 in the other field,
it will automatically multiply them and show 72.
Every time we change what's in the field, they will automatically
update the product below, here it's showing that 8 times 94 is 752.
I can enter another value here, 83 times 94, I can use a floating point,
decimal numbers, I can use negative numbers, etc.
So the question is, how do I accomplish this in React?
Where are the components?
Well, certainly we can make the entire thing one component.
And it's state is the different values and the product, and
it handles all of the rendering, and all of the user interaction.
One problem with that is that we want to re-render only the things that need
to be re-rendered, and not the entire component each time.
In this example, maybe, it doesn't matter.
But if you think about having lots of different values in the page,
we don't want them all to update at the same time.
Likewise, this component would not be reusable.
The point of React is that we can create reusable,
modular components to use in different web applications.
And here, there's perhaps too much tied to this one specific app.
It's tempting to do what we did last time, which is to have, for
instance, these text fields be components within this outer component.
But when they're modified, how would they notify the parent,
the outer component, that something needs to be changed?
We could just have three separate components, but
we're still on the same problem where we started where if one changes, for
instance the input box changes, how does it notify this other component?
So this solution that I hinted at, at the beginning of the lesson,
is to keep using composition where one component contains others.
Here, the entire application is one component that's
demonstrated with the red outer box shown here.
But that outer component will contain three inner components.
There are the two input boxes, shown in green here.
And then, shown here in blue, is the output or the product,
which is itself, another React component.
So it's a lot to keep track of, but it's actually a fairly graceful solution.
We'll start with the outer component which I've called the Multiplier.
The Multiplier has a constructor and a Multiplier has three parts to its state.
The first is the first input value, which will initialize to 0.
The second input value also initialized to 0.
And the product, of course, initialized to 0.
Here we see something we haven't seen in previous examples.
But what I'm doing here is creating a multiply property in this object and
I'm setting it to its own multiply function using bind.
Here I see the definition of my multiply function, which will take two parameters,
the id of the input box that's being changed and the value that is in that box.
If the id is 1, that means that this is input box number 1.
Then the multiplier component, the outer component, will set its state accordingly.
It'll set it's own input1 variable to whatever the value was in that input box
and then update the product by multiplying that value times whatever was input2.
If this was id number 2, it's the second input box that was changed.
Then we'll set the state accordingly by changing input two to that value,
and recalculating the product using whatever was input one.
Now you might ask, why not just set input1 or input2 in the state,
and then calculate the product as always being input1 times input2?
The reason is, if we call set state, and then call set state again, the first
change won't be seen by the second change until after this function is finished.
For that reason we need to have this code that sets the state depending on whether
id was 1 or 2.
Now here's the render function for our multiplier component.
This is going to return a div, and we're going to contain three other components.
The first two are the number input fields that we'll see in the next slide.
Each number input field has an id, and the number input field also has an action.
The action is a property that's passed to the number input field.
But what's different about this?
In past examples, the property has always been some sort of variable.
We initialized the string, we initialized an item, but
here, we're initializing it with a function.
That is we're passing a function from the multiplier, the parent,
to its child, the NumberInputField.
We'll do this for the second input field as well.
Setting its id to 2, and setting the same action, the same multiply function.
And then last, within the multiplier, we have the output field,
where the property of the output field will be the product set to the products
that we've calculated within the multiplier.
Now we'll see the NumberInputField component.
Recall that the NumberInputField was created when we rendered the multiplier.
NumberInputField is a react component, it has a constructor.
And we see again this short hand where we're going to bind the handleChange
function to a handleChange variable that we can later use.
Here is the handleChange function.
It's going to access it's props that were set when this
component was created and invoke this action function.
So action is part of the props and was set when this component
was created to be the multiply function in the multiplier component.
That's how this component,
NumberInputField, can call a function can call a function in
another component because that function was passed to it as a its props.
When it calls that function, it's going to pass its own ID and
its going to pass the value that's in the input box.
Then we have the render function which will render the input box and
then bind the handleChange property of this component to the onChange event.
And remember the handleChange property which was set up here is bound to
this handleChange function which is of course here.
If we look back at the multiplier component,
we can see that when the NumberInputField uses the action property to
call the function in the multiplier, it's going to set the state,
take the value that was in the input box, and recalculate the product.
Because we're calling setState in the multiplier,
this will call its render function which will then rerender the OutputField.
The OutputField is a component created in the multiplier.
In its props we set the product which is the multipliers calculated product.
OutputField is a React component and its render function is going to return
the text that reads the product is with the product that was passed to it.
And to include all of this in our HTML page all we need to do is include
the multiplier component and that will include everything else.
Now we're done with the basics of React.
We've seen how to create a component, and how a component can interact with other
components, and render dynamic HTML, based on their state.